A Finding Aid to the Ramón Guerrero Papers and Photographs, 1978-1993, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Ramón Guerrero papers and photographs
1978-1993
Archives of American Art
Guerrero, Ramon, 1946-1993
AAA.guerramo
Archival Resource Key
0.6 Linear feet
The papers and photographs of Cuban born American photographer Ramón Guerrero measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1978 to 1998. The collection is comprised of biographical material, correspondence, artist files, printed materials, and photographs by Guerrero that include portraits of Cuban American artists and several photographs relating to the Cuba-USA: The Next Generation exhibition in Chicago.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Ramón Guerrero papers and photographs were donated in 1997 by Maria Guerrero, widow of Ramón Guerrero.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Biographical / Historical
Ramón Guerrero (1946-1993) was a photographer in Miami, Florida. Guerrero was born in Camaguey, Cuba and came to the United States in 1962. After a brief stint in New York where he worked as a photographer's assistant at Mayo Studios, he returned to Miami in 1976 and opened his own studio. He is known for his series of still lifes and nudes that explore themes of life, death, time, and religion, as well as portraits of notable Cuban American artists.
Guerrero was the recipient of a grant from the National Endowment for the Arts, the Advertising Club of New York's Andy Award, and a Cintas Fellowship in 1990. He participated in the exhibitions Cuba-USA: The First Generation, Islands in the Stream: Seven Cuban American Artists, and Myths and Realities. Guerrero died in Miami in 1993.
Scope and Contents
The papers and photographs of Cuban born American photographer Ramón Guerrero measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1978 to 1998. The collection is comprised of biographical material, correspondence, artist files, printed materials, and photographs by Guerrero that include portraits of Cuban American artists. Also included are several photographs relating to the Cuba-USA: The Next Generation exhibition in Chicago, including one group photo and individual portraits of several of the participating artists.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as five series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1989-1993 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1978-1993 (Box 1; 6 folders)
Series 3: Artist Files, 1982-1993 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Materials, 1992-1993 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1982-1992 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Cuban American artists; Cuban American art; Latino and Latin American artists; Artists--Photographs; Expatriate artists -- Florida -- Miami; Artists -- Cuba; Portrait photography; Art, American--Florida--Miami; Photographers--Florida--Miami; Photographs; Cuba-USA: the next generation (1991 :Chicago, Ill.)
- Biographical Materials, 1989-1993; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of four appointment books for the years 1990 to 1993 and photocopies of guest book pages from the exhibition Myths and Realities.
  - Appointment Books, 1990-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
    4 books
  - Guest Book, Myths and Realities Exhibition, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Photocopies
- Correspondence, 1978-1993; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 6 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence is with the Cintas Foundation, Inc., Washington Project for the Arts, and galleries and schools regarding exhibitions and volunteering. A recommendation letter by Marta Gutierrez for Guerrero's application to the Florida Individual Artist Fellowship Program is also included.
  - Cintas Foundation Inc., Fellowship, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Exhibitions Correspondence, 1990-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Florida Individual Artist Fellowship Program, Recommendation from Marta Gutierrez, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence is with the Cintas Foundation, Inc., Washington Project for the Arts, and with galleries and schools regarding exhibitions and volunteering. A recommendation letter by Marta Gutierrez for Guerrero's application to the Florida Individual Artist Fellowship Program is also included.
  - Islands in the Stream: Seven Cuban American Artists Exhibition, Regarding, 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Volunteering, 1991-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Washington Project for the Arts, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Artist Files, 1982-1993; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Files for artists contain photographs of the artists and their artwork, invoices, and printed material.
  - Azaceta, Luis Cruz, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bencomo, Mario, 1986-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Boyte, Rob, 1989-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brito-Avellana, Maria, 1985-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cabrera, Lydia, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cubiles, Miguel - General, Correspondence, 1986-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cubiles, Miguel - Correspondence, 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Garcia York, Roberto, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Larraz, Julio, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Leiva, Nicolas, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Luis, Fernando M., undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Maldonado, Estuardo, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Martínez-Cañas, María, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Padura, Miguel, circa 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Peláez, Amelia, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Riverón, Enrique, 1982-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sorí, Susana, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Printed Materials, 1992-1993; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 2
  Clippings of reviews, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and newsletters relating to Guerrero and his photography are in this series.
  - Clippings, Reviews, circa 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Photographs, circa 1982-1992; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 2
  A self-portrait and photographs by Guerrero of Cuban American artists include portraits of Juan Abreu, Antonio Enrique Amaral, Luis Cruz Azaceta, Mario Bencomo, Maria Brito, Lydia Cabrera, José Martínez-Cañas, Maria Martínez-Cañas, Pablo Cano, Miguel Cubiles, Emilio Falero, Enrique Guy Garcia, Florencio Gelabert, Shirley Henderson, Lou Laurin-Lam, Raquel Lazaro, Nicolas Leiva, Guido Llinas, Fernando Luis, Laura Luna, Gina Pellon, Enrique and Noella Riverón, Lydia Rubio, Enrique Labrador-Ruiz, Guillermo Serrano, Frederic Snitzer, Cesar Trasobares, Estevan Vallejo, and Lorenzo Garcia Yega II. Also included are several photos taken in January of 1991 relating to the Cuba-USA: The Next Generation exhibition in Chicago, including one group photo and individual portraits of several of the participating artists, including Juan Boza, Maria Castagliola, Raquel Mendieta, Osvaldo Mesa, Cesar Trasobares, and Marc Zuver.
  Arrangement
  Portraits of Cuban American artists are arranged alphabetically by surname.
  - Self-Portrait, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Portraits of Cuban American Artists, A-G, circa 1982-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes a group photograph taken during the exhibition CUBA-USA: The First Generation-In Search of Freedom in Chicago, I.L.
  - Portraits of Cuban American Artists, H-Z, circa 1982-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)